Finding Aid for Arbornet and M-Net Records, 1985-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arbornet and M-Net Records 1985-2002
Arbornet.
2 linear feet
2012017 Bb 2
Arbornet and M-Net were early computer conferencing services based in Ann Arbor. Founded as separate platforms, they merged in 1992 to provide bulletin board conferences, live online chat, free email, a homepage, and learning resources to members of the Ann Arbor community. The collection includes material related to the development and administration of the systems, including records of board meetings and organizational finances.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Rex Roof (donor no. 10613 ) in 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Arbornet and M-Net were early computer conferencing services that were founded in the 1980s and based in Ann Arbor. M-Net was developed by Mike Meyers in 1982 as a free system and drew users from the local community, including university and high school students. As the system grew it began to encourage donations from users, in exchange for access to improved services.
Arbornet was founded in 1984 by Network Technologies International (NETI) as a profit making enterprise that provided similar services to M-Net. After failing to take off, Arbornet was abandoned by NETI in the spring of 1985 and was transformed by its users into a membership-based non-profit. M-Net was sold to Dave Parks in 1990, as issues surrounding censorship and open membership arose. Issues with the ownership and management of M-Net continued and it merged with Arbornet in 1992, with the Arbornet non-profit corporation taking over the operation of the M-Net computer system.
M-Net and Arbornet attempted to reframe themselves as an educational and community service organization, but met with resistance from their users. This shift also coincided with increased financial difficulty for the service. Since 1996, Arbornet and M-Net have survived largely on a month to month basis through donations from dedicated users.
The records of Arbornet and M-Net (2 linear feet) are arranged in three series: Administrative Files (0.7 linear feet), Background and Development (.6 linear feet), and Treasurer's Files (0.5 linear feet). The material in the collections reflects the challenges of cooperative management of an internet-based nonprofit, and the changes in online communities during the 1990s.
Subjects:
Arbornet.; M-Net (Organization); Computer conferencing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Internet--History.; Internet communication--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
M-Net (Organization)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files (0.7 linear feet) contain material related to the management of Arbornet and M-Net, including records of board meetings and member lists.
  - Arbornet NEW Center Sign-In Sheets and Lists (Box 1)
  - Board Meeting, 1999-2002, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Elections, 1994-2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Copyright, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - M-Net Compliance, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - M-Net Opinion Poll, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Space, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Users and Systems, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
- Background and Development
  The Background and Development (0.6 linear feet) series is composed of files dealing with the ongoing development of the M-Net platform. This material includes chronological files, publications, and material related to the development of the original Unix platform.
  - "A Partial History of Computer Conferencing in Ann Arbor", 2007 (Box 1)
  - Arbornet Chronological Files, 1996-2002, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - "Arbornet: Guide to the Internet", 1994 (Box 1)
  - ICAN, 1996 (Box 1)
  - M-Net Chronological Files, 1993, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Unix, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - WIN, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Yapp Administration Guide, 1997 (Box 2)
- Treasurer's Files
  The Treasurer's Files (0.5 linear feet) contain financial records and records of dues paying users. These files include financial plans, lists of expenses, and extensive user records.
  - Arbornet membership, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Coast to Coast, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1991 (Box 2)
  - Expenses, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
  - Financial Plan, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Financial statements, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Income, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
  - Membership lists and Dues Payments, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Status changes, 1996-1998, 6 folders (Box 2)